in Dam we also have a transistor that is
activated by the word line and that
connects the cell to the bit line but we
said that's the only transistor we have
the cell is made out of a simple
capacitor here so the idea is that to
write to this cell we will activate the
word line we put let's say A1 into the
bit Line This transistor connects the
capacitor to the bit line now what
happens is R1 effectively charges this
capacitor once we deactivate the word
line the capacitor retains the value
that corresponds to a one if we want to
write a zero we activate the word line
the capacitor is now connected to the
bit line that is connected to a zero
voltage and we empty this capacitor into
the bit line thus now our capacitor
becomes a zero value now when we
disconnect the word line the capacitor
has nothing in it so it retains the
value of zero so as you can see the bit
is really stored in this capacitor when
it's charged we are storing a one when
it's not charged we are storing a zero
so what's the problem here well the
problem is that this transistor is not a
perfect switch it's a little bit leaky
here it's not a problem because if it's
a little bit leaky these two are strong
enough to retain the voltage at you know
let's say 1 and zero or Z and one while
these are not trying to defeat them but
here our capacitor is slowly leaking
into the bit line and eventually gets
empty so one problem with DM is that it
will lose this bit over time and that
means that periodically we have to
actually read out this bit figure out
what it was and write it back in at full
Voltage so that it can again leak for a
while before it gets lost another
problem with dram that you don't have
with SRAM is that once we open the word
line the capacitor drains into the bit
line we can sense what the value was but
the capacitor is no longer fully charged
this is called destructive read when you
read a DRM cell you have to write it
back in it loses the value as it gets
red so this is what is usually called a
6t cell or six transistor cell there are
two transistors that are there for
connecting to the cell and there are
four transist s in the cell itself
because each of the inverters has two
transistors this is of course a 1T cell
now the area occupied by an SRAM cell
obviously is the area occupied by about
six
transistors the area of the dram cell it
looks like it's the area of one
transistor and the area of a capacitor
the bigger this capacitor the longer it
can retain something that corresponds to
a one or a zero before it gets lost so
we want this capacitor to be big a
capacitor can be viewed as two metal
plates placed very close to each other
the bigger the area of the plates the
bigger the capacitance of the capacitor
it can keep more charge so it looks like
to make a good dram cell we will have to
make a big cell because this capacitor
will need a lot of metal area to build
large plates but this is not how we
build this capacitor the transistor and
the capacitor itself are actually built
as a single transistor in a technology
that is called trench cell so this end
of this transistor is simply buried
deeply into the Silicon substrate when
we manufacture transistors so really the
capacitor is kind of buried under the
transistor so we really get the area of
the transistor itself and not much
around it you can see also that the dram
cell can be smaller because it doesn't
need this second bit line we just need
one so that also makes it slightly
smaller we don't need as much wiring
there